Hill, James C. Arbitration Files 5538
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
James C. Hill Arbitration Files
1941-1962
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Hill, James C.
5538
67 cubic feet
67 linear ft.
Decisions.
Documents relating to the U.S. National War Labor Board and the U.S. Wage Stabilization Board, as well as general subject files.
3833936
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, January 15, 2004
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 18, 2019
Biographical / Historical
Arbitrator, mediator, employee and panel member of federal labor dispute and wage stabilization agencies.
The National War Labor Board, a tri-partite body established in 1942 by President Franklin D. Roosevelt, was charged with acting as an arbitration board in labor-management dispute cases, thereby preventing work stoppages which might hinder the war effort. It was also responsible for determining wage adjustments in accordance with anti-inflationary wage stabilization criteria and policies.
The Board was initially divided into twelve Regional Administrative Boards which handled both labor dispute settlement and wage stabilization functions for specific geographic regions. The National Board further decentralized in 1943, when it established special tri-partite commissions and panels to deal with particular industries on a national basis.
The Wage Stabilization Board was created as a constituent division of the Economic Stabilization Agency by Executive Order 10161 of September 9, 1950, under the authority of the Defense Production Act of 1950, to control wages and salaries during the Korean War emergency period. An executive order of April 21, 1951 reestablished the Board with power to assist the president in settling industrial disputes. In July of 1952, the Board was reconstituted under legislative authority but stripped of its function in the area of labor disputes. Wage controls were suspended in February of 1953 and the Board was terminated the following April. The Board, while it functioned, was a tripartite body representing labor, industry and the public. To expedite its activities, regional offices were established, including that in New York.
Scope and Contents
Organizational documents include minutes of the National, Regional and Reviews and Appeals Committee of the U.S. National War Labor Board; case reports of the U.S. National War Labor Board Reviews and Appeals Committee (ca. 1942-1945); conferences; reports and transcripts of executive sessions of the U.S. Wage Stabilization Board (1950-1952); miscellaneous procedural and policy manuals; memoranda; opinions of general counsels; summaries of the Board's decisions and actions; and bulletins and press releases of general wage stabilization regulations (1951), and of the U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics (1951-1955).
Readers' files consist of memoranda of the U.S. Wage Stabilization Board, Region 2, and letters of Board members (1951-1953). Materials cover disposition of dispute cases in the following industries: agriculture, coal, ore extraction, non-metallic, quarrystone, contracting, meat, dairy, grain, bakery and confectionery, beverages, tobacco, textiles, apparel, lumber, wood products, furniture, pulp and paper products, printing, publishing, chemicals, chemical products, plastics, drugs, petroleum, rubber, leather, stone, clay, glass, cement, metals, rolling and forging, machinery, engines and turbines, construction and handling, machine tools, office and computing machines, electric and electronic equipment, transportation equipment, vehicles, instruments, transportation, utilities, trade, finance, business, and recreational services. Disputed issues include wages, holiday, hours of work, shift differential, insurance, position classification, wage adjustment, wage bonus, profit sharing, sick leave, fringe benefits, disability insurance, overtime, transfer, pension, merit pay, back pay, military leave, funeral leave, meal allowance, and protective clothing.
General subject files include press releases and memoranda of the U.S. National War Labor Board, U.S. Wage Stabilization Board, and U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics. Files also include manuscript notes and miscellaneous printed materials pertaining to ability to pay, wages, appeals, wage bonus, Defense Production Act, dismissal, discrimination, discipline, fair labor standards, fringe benefits, grievance and arbitration procedure, health and welfare, holiday, job evaluation, position classification, jurisdictional dispute, productivity, wage-price policy, hours of work, shift differential, strikes, supervisors, wage adjustments, transfers, and disputes in aircraft, airframe, automobile, construction, copper, transportation, maritime, lumber, meat, petroleum, non-ferrous metals, steel, railroad, airline, rubber, shipbuilding and trucking industries (1942-1953).
Organizational documents include minutes of the National, Regional and Reviews and Appeals Committee of the U.S. National War Labor Board; case reports of the U.S. National War Labor Board Reviews and Appeals Committee (ca. 1942-1945); conferences; reports and transcripts of executive sessions of the U.S. Wage Stabilization Board (1950-1952); miscellaneous procedural and policy manuals; memoranda; opinions of general counsels; summaries of the Board's decisions and actions; and bulletins and press releases of general wage stabilization regulations (1951), and of the U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics (1951-1955).
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5703: James C. Hill Additional Files
Arrangement
Series I - National War Labor Board - Wage Stabilization Board
Sub-Series A. Minutes, 1951-1953 Sub-Series B. General Subject Files, 1943-19555 Sub-Series C. Appeals, Minutes and Reports Sub-Series D. Transcripts - Executive Session - National Wage Stabilization Board Sub-Series E. Conference Reports of Economic Stabilization Agency - Executive Meeting - National Wage Stabilization Board Sub-Series F. Readers File (Numerical Order) - Memoranda, 1952 Sub-Series G. Miscellaneous Publications, Reports, Instruction Sheets Sub-Series H. Manual of Instructions Sub-Series I. Releases and Memos, 1942-1953
Series II - Arbitration Files
Sub-Series A. Board of Education (New York City and Others) Sub-Series B. Arbitration Files
Series III - Emergency Boards
Sub-Series A. #152 - Pan American World Airways vs. Transport Workers of America Sub-Series B. #159 - Brotherhood of Railway Signalmen [vs. Various National Railway Carriers?]. Emergency Board 159. Sub-Series C. Board of Inquiry - Republic Aviation.
Absenteeism -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Airlines -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Automobile industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Broadcasting -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Cement industries -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Chemical industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Confectionery industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Container industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Education -- New Jersey; Arbitration, Industrial -- Electric industries -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Electronic industries -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Metal-workers -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Newspaper publishing -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Paper industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Petroleum industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Publishing -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Railroads -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Steel industry -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Teachers -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Telecommunication -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- Transportation -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- United States -- Cases; Bargaining unit -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Bargaining unit -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Contracting out -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Contracting out -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Discrimination in employment -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Discrimination in employment -- United States; Employee attitudes -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Employee attitudes -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Employee fringe benefits -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Employee rights -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Employees, Dismissal of -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Employees, Dismissal of -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Employees, Dismissal of -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Employees -- Dismissal of -- United States; Employees, Training of -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Employees, Training of -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Employees, Transfer of -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Employees, Transfer of -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Grievance procedures -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Grievance procedures -- United States; Hours of labor -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Industrial hygiene -- United States; Industrial mobilization -- United States; Industrial productivity -- United States; Industrial safety -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Job descriptions -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Job descriptions -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Job vacancies -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Labor discipline -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Labor discipline -- United States; Airlines -- United States; Labor disputes -- Aircraft industry -- United States; Labor disputes -- Lumber industry -- United States; Labor disputes -- Merchant marine -- United States; Labor disputes -- Nonferrous metal industries -- United States; Labor disputes -- Railroads -- United States; Labor disputes -- Shipbuilding industry -- United States; Labor productivity -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Labor productivity -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Layoffs -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Management rights -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- Railroads -- United States; Misconduct -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Vacations, Employee -- Law and legislation -- United States; Performance appraisal -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Position classification -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Retirement -- Law and legislation -- United States; Seniority, Employee -- Law and legislation -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- United States; Technological innovations -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Technological innovations -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Unfair labor practices -- United States; Wage-price policy -- United States; Wages -- Agriculture -- United States; Airlines -- Employees -- Salaries, etc. -- United States; Wages -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Wages -- Automobile industry -- United States; Wages -- Chemical industry -- United States; Wages -- Clothing industry -- United States; Wages -- Construction industry -- United States; Wages -- Pharmaceutical industry employees -- United States; Wages -- Electric industries -- United States; Wages -- Flour and feed trade -- United States; Wages -- Food industry -- United States; Wages -- Furniture industry -- United States; Wages -- Glass manufacture -- United States; Wages -- Leather industry -- United States; Wages -- Machine industry -- United States; Wages -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Wages -- Mining industry -- United States; Wages -- Paper industry -- United States; Wages -- Petroleum industry -- United States; Wages -- Plastics industry -- United States; Wages -- Printing industry -- United States; Wages -- Publishing -- United States; Wages -- Railroads -- United States; Wages -- Recreation industry -- New York (State); Wages -- Rubber industry -- United States; Wages -- Steel industry -- United States; Wages -- Textile industry -- New England; Wages -- Tobacco workers -- United States; Wages -- Transportation -- United States; Wages -- United States -- State supervision; Wages -- Utilities -- United States; White collar workers -- Salaries, etc. -- United States; War and emergency powers -- United States; Work assignment -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Work assignments -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Employee rules -- United States; Working conditions -- Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Working conditions -- Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Labor disputes -- United States; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States; Hill, James C., 1914-; American Airlines, Inc.; American Bakery and Confectionery Workers' International Union; American Cyanamid Company; American Smelting and Refining Company; Anaconda American Brass Company; Arma Corporation; Atomic Trades and Labor Council; Bassick Company; Bell Telephone Company of Pennsylvania; Bethlehem Steel Corporation; Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen; Budd Company; Continental Can Company, Inc.; Eastern Air Lines, Inc.; Eastern Carriers' Conference Committee; Federation of Telephone Workers of Pennsylvania; Flight Engineers' International Association; Gaynor News Company; General Motors Corporation; Hershey Chocolate Corporation; Independent Workers' Union of the Budd Company; Ingersoll-Rand Company; International Air Line Pilots Association; International Alliance of Theatrical, Stage Employees and Moving Picture Operators of the U.S. and Canada; International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers; International Association of Machinists. Republic Lodge; International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite, and Paper Mill Workers; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America. Local 99 (Rochester, N.Y.); International Chemical Workers Union (1944- ); International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers; International Union of Mine, Mill and Smelter Workers; International Union, United Automobile, Aircraft, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America; Metropolitan News Company; National Association of Broadcast Employees and Technicians; National Maritime Union of America; National Railway Labor Conference (U.S.); New York (N.Y.). Board of Education; Newark Newsdealers Supply Company; Newspaper and Mail Deliverers' Union of New York City and Vicinity; Oil, Chemical, and Atomic Workers International Union; Pan American World Airways, Inc.; Publishers' Association of New York City; Republic Aviation Corporation; Revere Copper and Brass Company; Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committee; St. Regis Paper Company; Standard Rolling Mills; Technical, Office and Professional Workers Union; Television Broadcasting Studio Employees; Texaco, Inc.; Trans World Airlines, Inc.; Transport Workers Union of America; Triangle Publications, Inc.; Union Carbide Corporation; United Cement, Lime, and Gypsum Workers International Union; United Federation of Teachers; United States. Emergency Board No. 152; United States. Emergency Board No. 159; United States. National War Labor Board (1942-1945); United States. National War Labor Board (1942-1945); United States. National War Labor Board (1942-1945).Reviews and Appeals Committee; United States. Wage Stabilization Board; United States. Wage Stabilization Board. Region 2; United Steelworkers of America; Universal Atlas Cement; Western Carriers' Conference Committee; Westinghouse Electric Corporation
3833936
- Series I - National War Labor Board - Wage Stabilization Board
  - Sub-Series A. Minutes, 1951-1953
    - Sub-Series 1. Regional Board Minutes
      - Regional Board Minutes, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Scope and Contents
        10/3/51 - 1/18/52
      - Regional Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        1/23/52 - 2/14/52
      - Regional Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        2/18/52 - 3/13/52
      - Regional Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        3/19/52 - 4/3/52
      - Regional Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        4/9/52 - 4/30/52
      - Regional Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        5/1/52 - 6/12/52
      - Regional Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        6/18/52 - 7/22/52
      - Regional Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        7/23/52 - 8/15/52
      - Regional Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        8/20/52 - 9/12/52
      - Regional Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        9/17/52 - 9/26/52
      - Regional Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        10/1/52 - 10/15/52
      - Regional Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        10/15/52 - 10/22/52
      - Regional Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        10/23/52 - 11/14/52
      - Regional Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
        11/19/52 - 12/16/52
      - Regional Board Minutes, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        12/16/52 - 1/7/53
      - Regional Board Minutes, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 8)
        1/7/53 - 1/26/53
    - Sub-Series 2. National Board Minutes
      - National Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - National Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        6/15/52 - 7/18/52
      - National Board Minutes, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 3)
        7/22/52 - 9/16/52
      - National Board Minutes, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 4)
        9/17/52 - 1/15/53
    - Sub-Series 3. Review and Appeals Committee Minutes
      - Review and Appeals Committee Minutes, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sub-Series B. General Subject Files, 1943-1955
    - Ability to Pay, 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Abnormal Base Period Cases (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Acme Bottling, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Aircraft and Airframe, 1943-1945 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Airframe Industry, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Airframe Memo's and Decisions Inc. - West Coast Airframes, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Annual Improvement Factor, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Appeals Cases, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Appeals Procedure, 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Arbitration, 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Arbitration - Policy - National War Labor Board, 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Arbitration Procedure, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Association Filing, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Auto Mechanics (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Automatic Progression, 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Automobile Industry, 1942-1943 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Board Policy, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Bonus Cases, 1951-1952 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Bonus Payments, 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Building Service Industry, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Bureau of Labor Statistics - Special Reports, 1951-1955 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Bureau of Labor Statistics Surveys - Albany - Schenectady - Troy, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Bureau of Labor Statistics Surveys - Middlesex County, New Jersey, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Bureau of Labor Statistics Surveys - New York and Northern New Jersey, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Bureau of Labor Statistics Surveys - New York City, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Bureau of Labor Statistics Surveys - Newark, New Jersey, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Bureau of Labor Statistics Surveys - Northern New Jersey, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Bureau of Labor Statistics Surveys - Syracuse, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Bureau of Labor Statistics Surveys - Trenton, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Bureau of Labor Statistics Surveys - Utica - Rome, New York, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Bureau of Labor Statistics Surveys - Union Agreements, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Bureau of Labor Statistics Surveys - Wage Surveys, General, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Congress of Industrial Organizations Case Report, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Coal, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Coal Industry, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Commission Payments, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Commission Payments, Decreases, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Commission Salesman, 1943-1944 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Commissions - National War Labor Board, 1943-1945 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Compliance, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Compliance and Enforcement, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Conference of Regional Directors of Case Analysis, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Construction Industry Stabilization Commission, 1951-1952 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Construction Industry - Wage Stabilization Board, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Copper Cases, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Critical Occupations, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Decontrol Board Material, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Decreases - Draft and Notes, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Defense Production Act, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Delegated Agencies, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Delegation of Authority (Regional Boards), 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Delegation of Authority (Staff), 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Discharge and Reinstatement, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Discrimination, 1943-1944 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Disputes, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Disputes - Wage Stabilization Board, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Doodling (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Editorial Digest (National War Labor Board), 1945 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Employee Discipline, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Equal Pay for Equal Work, 1942-1945 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Executive Orders, 1943-1944 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Fact Finding Board - Greyhound Bus Dispute, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Fact Finding Board - International Harvester Case, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Fact Finding Board - Meat Packing Industry, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Fact Finding Board - Oil Panel, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Fact Finding Board - Pacific Coast Shoreline, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Fact Finding Board - Pacific Gas and Electric, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Fact Finding Board - Steel Fact Finding Board, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Fact Finding Board - Western Union Telegraph, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Fair Labor Standards Act, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Federal Employees, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Field Liaison, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Five Cent Policy, 1953 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Fringe Benefits, General, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Fringe Issues, 1945 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - General Motors, 1945-1946 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - General Order 31, 1944-1945 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Grievance Procedure, 1944-1945 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Grievance Procedure (General), 1943-1945 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Health and Welfare, 1951-1952 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Hill - Manuscript on National Wage Stabilization Board (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Holidays, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Incentive Plans, 1951-1952 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Individual Wage Adjustments (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Industry Commissions (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Inter-plant Inequities, 1951-1952 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Intra-plant Inequities, 1951-1953 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Intra-plant Wage Relationships, 1945 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Job Evaluation and Reclassification, 1944-1952 (Box 11, Folder 10)